[Music]
in 1991 Richard tarnis released the
passion of the Western mind a vast
history of Western thought it became an
unexpected bestseller in it he argued
that Western skepticism and materialism
had been a heroic project but had also
created an intellectual prison and that
it was creating a crisis 27 years on
where are we in that process in terms of
where we are historically and in this
moment of history I think we're at a
very pivotal place very volatile very
uncertain and all of these qualities are
very characteristic of this threshold of
the death rebirth process because you
have to have an uncertain outcome you
have to have the conviction of
uncertainty for such a transformation to
actually be successful you you have to
really feel that everything is at stake
and it might not work out for the the
moral transformation to take place you
can't we all know how what people who
have a near-death experience tend to
come out of it with a rather rather
radical change of their life philosophy
it has a more potent effect in like five
seconds than almost anything else you
can have and but you can't have a
pretend near-death experience for it to
have that kind of moral spiritual
psychological transformation you really
have to feel everything's at stake and
the result is uncertain and that's just
how we're experiencing it today only on
a collective scale the everything that
Joseph Campbell described as the
initiative experience like the the the
crisis of meaning the being isolated
from the rest of the community the the
sense of facing one's own mortality
the the personal suffering the the you
know the the deconstruction of the old
identity or you like that
an old self is dying everything that I
just described which is happening on the
personal level in an initiation is
what's happening on the collective level
to our human civilization except it's
now we're looking at planetary mortality
rather than just as an individual
person's mortality and we're looking at
reconstructing reconceiving the death of
it we're having to go through a dying of
our whole identity about how who we are
relative to the nature who we are
relative to the cosmos and are we really
living in a disenchanted cosmos in which
were the only intelligent spiritual
being in town or are we embedded in an
in sold universe of inconceivable depth
and mystery and intelligence in of which
we are an expression we were we are the
cosmos in human form and it's that that
happens in the state of spiritual
rebirth that we reconnect to the sense
that that we are we are cosmic beings
and we're also participating in
something much bigger than us so we
simultaneously are humbled by the
experience but also exalted by
reconnecting to the hole that has
infused through us so I think we're at a
very dicey place right now where the
question is will enough people
individuals go through this kind of
profound inner transformation an inner
work inner journey to be able to go
through what is basically a kind of
symbolic spiritual death so that we
don't have to do it literally and we've
already set in motion destructive forces
and some of those forces are
are you know already affecting the world
and probably are going to continue and
the question is will the kind of
near-death experience that we are kind
of going through in sort of slow motion
right now be sufficient to catalyze
enough of a psycho spiritual
transformation in enough people that
those people can serve as centers of
insight and equilibrium so to inform the
whole in a way it it doesn't take
everybody to do this but it takes enough
people who are able to their sensibility
and their transformation can ripple out
you know through through the kind of
work that you you you do with your
organization and with the with the kinds
of access that we have through podcasts
and and things that aren't being put on
the mainstream channels of television or
even taught in the universities I think
that can ripple out enough where if
enough individuals are carrying that
transformation it can actually help
catalyze a larger transformation in the
collective because it's at just such
moments of instability that that kind of
chaotic disequilibrium can suddenly
reconfigure in a new way in ways that
are not possible
when it's not so volatile so that's
that's my fervent hope and maybe I'll
just end this with the idea that hope
itself can play a role I think to have
hope and faith in the darkness is very
important and in some sense it's only in
dark periods that that you develop faith
and hope with everything's just light
and glorious and hunky-dory
you don't develop those muscles you it's
something that happens on in challenging
times and that develops the the moral
spiritual fiber that we need and hope is
one of those virtues of that I think
cultivating that it will be very
important I read passion of the Western
mind at university back in 93 94 and I'd
say it probably had the most impact of
anything I've ever read as a kind of map
of the history of Western thinking we're
the kind of the bind that we've got
ourselves into
in terms of Western philosophy and we're
how we might get out of it and for me a
lot of what you wrote about then still
feels very very current it still seemed
like a very accurate description of
where we are and what we were going
through I'm assuming that we've got a
fairly big audience at the moment a lot
of them have come to us through Jordan
Peterson and the interesting thing for
me about Jordan Peterson and the IDW
intellectual dark web movement seems to
be that the Internet is facilitating a
kind of intellectual awakening there's a
lot of people devouring young they're
devouring a lot of kind of very deep
philosophical material through through
the doorway of Jordan Peterson which is
really exciting and in as rebel wisdom
what we're trying to do is to to really
examine some of these huge ideas and say
what are the ideas that have been sort
of maybe on the fringes of our culture
you could say Young is kind of on the
fringes of our culture and we've always
been sort of out there in the New Age
and hugely influential thinker but but
certainly not part of the mainstream and
I'd argue that you are one of those
thinkers as well hugely influential in
many different areas but but never kind
of part of the mainstream I'd love if
you could just introduce yourself and
tell me a little bit about your your
background life story and in two minutes
I was born in Geneva Switzerland of
American parents that grew up in in the
United States and I was educated
up through high school by by Jesuits and
and nuns before that and kind of got a
pretty solid grounding in in you know at
Greek and Latin and the classics and and
that it kind of imbued in the
appreciation for for the the cultural
intellectual spiritual legacy of the
West and so I was kind of putting
together all these different you know
attempting to integrate these different
influences and then I heard about Esalen
Institute in California when I was there
which in California I when I was still
at Harvard is where I first heard about
it and it sounded like a place where in
a sense then the new a new horizon was
opening up of thinkers teachers
practical also putting into practice
what these new ideas were that were
being drawn from many different sources
from shamanic traditions from ancient
mystical Asian traditions from Western
esotericism
as well as contemporary psychological
practices their therapeutic so yeah for
people who don't know what s elinoz s
alone is now pretty much universally
recognized as the sort of the granddaddy
of the human potential movement right
and Mother Church of the human potential
movement it was called in those years
yeah you can say you've got a Buddha
behind you so we're in a were in a kind
of New Age book shop and Esalen was sort
of seen as the a place where a lot of
Eastern traditions came in but what's
really fascinating about your work is
that you have a huge respect for an
understanding of the Western tradition
as well
I drank deeply from the wisdom of the
east and at a certain point it's in
night in my 20s I realized that it
wasn't an East versus West thing and in
fact there was a great deal of
wisdom and depth in the West that I I I
was informed by and I felt that in my
generations desire to kind of wipe the
slate clean overthrow the the the
oppressive ideas and structures of my of
our parents and previous generations
that we were cutting ourselves off from
from our own historical legacy from our
from our ancestry and and that that
would be a kind of mutilation and that
what we needed to do was to retrieve
what was profound in that tradition
while also keeping a clear eye for the
shadow of that tradition which we tended
to be unconscious of in the promotion of
whether it was progress or monotheistic
judeo-christian religious thought and so
I was always trying to kind of keep hold
that that tension of opposites as Jung
would say the importance of holding
multiple values that can be in tension
with each other and if you can not
prematurely fall into one or the other
and and then demonize the other or some
on negate it but if you can hold
faithfully that tension then there seems
to be something in the natural unfolding
of the human psyche and of life that
moves towards a creative synthesis of
what is being kind of loyally held as as
as opposites in tension and that that's
pretty much what I did and what I sought
to do and and so passion Western 9 was
one example of that even to the point of
also seeking to do that with ideas about
the masculine and the feminine as well
mmm-hmm to to recognize that there's
something deep going on in in our time
that needs needs addressing involving
the involving gender but also involving
the archetypal dimension behind gender
you
you mentioned synthesis there and that's
really what excites me about the
potential of this moment for for
intellectual synthesis you you start the
epilogue to passion of the west of mine
with a quote from Robert Bellah which i
think is a really profound quote and
what may be sort of bring up on the
screen I try to remember it's something
like we may be seeing the the
reintegration of consciousness that will
be not on the basis of any single
understanding of reality but the
understand that we need to move between
different languages different different
scientific and imaginative vocabularies
and and the idea of not ever falling
into the illusion that one particular
interpretation of reality is reality
itself but being constantly open to the
fact that we are always speaking you
know symbolically metaphorically about
about a mystery and and so we have to
keep a kind of humility a kind of
epistemological modesty as we approach
the mystery of things and and Robert
dalla who I deeply valued as a as a
friend and a teacher his great book
religion and human evolution that he
finished just before he died 14-year
project just a magnificent work anyway
Bela really carried that he wrote that
in 1969 and and it is a beautiful
rendering of our need to hold a a
plurality of perspectives as and and not
fall into some single literal
understanding the reason I brought up
the Robert Bellah quote is that I I see
some parallels with this intellectual
dark web that's arisen Jordan Peterson
what why I sort of got very deeply into
Jordan Peterson was recognizing that he
represents a real synthesis he uses the
Jungian model but he also links it to
the evolutionary model he uses
evolutionary biology uses psychology he
uses developmental psychology Jean
Piaget to talk about the evolution of
morality and synthesizes many different
ways of looking at the world and then
you have within the the same IDW
constellation someone like Brett
Weinstein who is a very very deep
evolutionary biologist who maps on what
he understands to what Peterson
understand and says yes there's that
there's a real here he actually told me
all all true maps must converge so this
sort of sense that there is the
potential for all of these different
maps moving towards a similar point I I
wonder and I'm hopeful that this great
intellectual awakening could be the time
of that of that great intellectual
synthesis yes you know I think it has to
happen but because there is so much I
mean on the one hand anybody with a with
a good contemporary you know modern
early postmodern education had sees the
unmistakable value of of you know
evolutionary Sciences of of the sciences
generally etc but if they are
sufficiently broad-minded and curious
and open haven't been shut down inside
into a into an a narrow perspective they
they recognize that statistics and
mechanistic scientific explanations do
not capture the full experience of human
reality
and anybody that does deep inner inner
inner work or journeys or sacred
medicine rituals or an LSD experience
will have a glimpse that there is
something more as William James would
put a capital s capital M something more
than is explicable by our by our
philosophies as you know Shakespeare's
there are more things in heaven and
earth Horatio than are dreamt of in our
philosophy so I think we we we have
these what can be warring sides and it
within all of us I think of it within
the West in particular as a conflict
between the Enlightenment with its
rationalist of scientific loyalties its
its allegiance to the modern mind you
might say and romanticism in the broad
sense that goes right up to the
psychedelic counterculture of the 60s
ensler which is which the modern soul is
loyal to as it were if we can make that
distinction and we all have that in our
in our being we all we all have
romanticism and the Enlightenment as
essential to who we are but there's
something about the way the modern
worldview emerged in which the the
rationalist scientific enlightenment
more or less has the center of gravity
for understanding the external physical
natural world and the while romanticism
is what speaks to our souls where we
where we we read our poetry we take
seriously
we're moved by our music we take
seriously the the artistic epiphanies
that open up to us a deeper view of
reality we we appreciate the the
spiritual experiences we have when we
are walking through a redwood forest or
watching a sunset over the over the
ocean the these are precious to us in
ways that can't be explained by a
reductionist scientific view so we have
both of these loyalties within us and
until we have that some deep
reconnecting between this the inner and
the outer as it were between mind and
soul or between the Enlightenment and
romanticism also between east and west
also we could say between north and
south if we bring in that idea of the
you know the the larger range of of
cultures and and cultural traditions
that are carried in the in the two
northern southern hemispheres and how
important that integration is for our
future and then finally between the
human being and the and the rest of the
of the Earth's community that that
separation has been catastrophic and
that separation has roots in in both the
Western scientific and religious
tradition in complex ways so there's a
number of fundamental healings of of
these schisms or bifurcations these
these polarities that the future of our
of our species really depends on I think
moving into a in integration and you you
have a really beautiful way of
describing that we we have attempted to
purge ourselves of any anthropomorphic
projections towards the world but what
we've all turned on has created the
ultimate and morphic projection would
you like to explain what what kind of as
an overview what is the situation we
find ourselves in and then what that
synthesis might look like it's a great
paradox because I think we can see how
the the modern mind from
you know Descartes and bacon and Locke
onward were very much focused on moving
out of an anthropocentric point of view
and you can actually see obviously the
Copernican revolution is seen as being
like the the ERM moment the the primal
transformation out of an assumed
cosmology in which the earth is the
center and therefore this is seen that
the human being is as the center of
cosmic design as it were and and then
suddenly we're a spinning moving planet
one amongst many and then there turns
out there's billions of Suns in a galaxy
that itself is one of billions of
galaxies so you have just this sequence
of breaking out of the anthropocentric
perspective this is kind of how the
story would be told you see and and
until we become seen as being radically
peripheral and part of that movement
towards cleansing our perception of
anthropocentric assumptions is to
believe that only the human being is
capable of meaning and purpose and if
you if you think that the world outside
the human being is carrying meaning and
purpose as for example when a
synchronicity happens and there's some
some powerful seems as if life has
conspired to suddenly bring together a
coincidence of such uncanny
meaning - - on that you that it it kind
of shifts your consciousness of like wow
there's something going on here that's
mysterious and the the the mainstream
sceptical point of view on this would be
if you think that's the case then you're
projecting what is
basically a human meaning onto the
nonhuman world and that's a basic
epistemological error it's childish
thinking it's it's it suggests delusions
of self reference and if you do a lot of
that we may recommend that you see a
psychiatrist and and perhaps have
medication and behind this sequence of
thinking is the conviction that only the
human being is a locus of attention
intention agency spirit soul purposeful
conscious intelligence and that the
world itself apart from the human is or
perhaps a few of the more complex higher
mammals and birds that aside from that
really human beings are the exclusive
locus of conscious purposeful
intelligence and the world apart from
the human is unconscious purposeless and
meaningless and that only human beings
have to find value and meaning that can
through the development of their
rational capacities and so forth which
he'd like into a kind of mental prison
that we've made for ourselves yes but it
was a liberating move at first mmm
because the because it was an attempt to
break out of a particular cosmology
ideology that had become very confining
it what was the word used fatalistic yes
that you that human beings were not in
control of their own destiny that either
the the cosmos or nature or a
transcendent God was determining our
reality and we needed to break out of
that and just
see that human beings had to define
their own reality so it's very
empowering to have that assumption but
in cleansing the the perception of of
any potential anthropocentric and
anthropomorphic projections onto nature
we fell into a trap because that too is
a kind of assumption as Rupert Sheldrake
says the assumption that the world is a
machine and that we are the one
conscious purposeful intelligence
presumes that that the that the machine
is something that is found in a state of
nature but in fact the machine is just
something created by human beings
natures of much more mysterious
phenomenon and in many ways I'll just
make two points on this one is that the
assumption that only human beings are
capable of meaning and purpose is an
enormous inflation of the human beings
as if we have taken all the potential
meaning and purpose that was seen but by
every other culture before the modern as
pervading nature the cosmos the earth
animals plants the heavens it's as if
like a vacuum cleaner we've sucked that
all up and locate really relocated it
inside the human cranium and and claim
this for ourselves alone which is a
rather remarkable act of human hubris if
you step back and look at it from that
point of view and the the corollary of
that is if you look at the pride that
modern take about we are the first ones
that recognize that the earth is moving
we are not the center of the universe
etcetera why is it that indigenous
cultures who weren't aware of the
moving tend to be much less
anthropocentric in their practice of
life than modern civilization which has
been so anthropocentric that it's that
it's crashing the biosphere with its
industrialized exploitation of the
natural environment and and radical
upsetting of the of the ecological
balances to the point that we have
catalyzed mass extinctions and and
melting of polar ice caps and extreme
climate events that are are really
causing you know tremendous hardship for
many species including our own most
vulnerable members of our own species so
there's been a great price that has been
played paid for the hubris of this
appropriation of all meaning and purpose
into the human being in the effort to
free ourselves of anthropocentric
assumptions it's one of those paradoxes
the the the unforeseen consequences of
good intentions that characterize
history because that's the other thing
about the The Passion of the Western
mind it as you said before it's a very
much a two sided story there's a sense
of this kind of great Apollonian project
to free ourselves from nature that is
that is a very positive project in many
ways but also there is a shadow side to
it as well in terms of how much it's cut
ourselves off from a lot of from nature
itself obviously but also from some of
our own inner knowing and this sort of
rationality and I guess you you alluded
to sort of masculine and feminine before
which is a one way of looking at it sort
of the intuition versus of the
rationality what do you think this
synthesis because you you you talk about
the potential for synthesis especially
in the epilogue to passion of the
Western mind what do you think the
synthesis looks like what do we need to
recognize and what
we need to integrate well I've spoken of
a number of the kinds of synthesis I
have in mind well between you'd say
between mind and heart also between mind
and body to get in touch with our by our
our bodies really are one way of putting
it is that we we need to recognize that
all the faculties that we have as human
beings are necessary for us to cultivate
to be able to to adequately register the
richness of of reality that a kind of
narrow-minded almost puritanical
rationality and narrow empiricism that
doesn't pay attention to the breadth of
human experience for example but is is
very quantitatively limited then to that
extent we are going to be really cut off
from our from the full range of of what
reality is about we're going to be
locked up in a kind of prison that could
could be very destructive as we're
seeing in practice because a little bit
of knowledge can be a dangerous thing
and a lot of knowledge from a very
narrow perspective which is what I would
argue is the mainstream epistemology can
be a catastrophic lead ange er esteem I
would say so one integration is of all
these different we need our relational
intelligence our emotional intelligence
our the full range of the imaginative
and intuitive capacities are our somatic
intelligence kinesthetic aesthetic how
important beauty is for for
illuminating what is important in in
life and deep beauty not shallow beauty
and to be able to recognize what is deep
or what is shallow these are these are
kind of educational goals as it were
that I think we are our educational
systems need to integrate into and
cultivate in in our in our students so
that we just don't all end up as kind of
technicians working with dashboard
knowledge as Olin Barfield put it could
I address one point that you mentioned
about the rationality and intuition and
it's connection to feminine and
masculine or masculine feminine I've
I've gone through of course I'm aware of
jordan Peterson's number of comments
he's made along along the line of what's
what's feminine and once masculine and
core he's drawing on among other things
certain things that Jung wrote Carl
Gustav Jung and in that epilogue of
passion of the Western I also talked
about at the at the very end the idea
that we we have had a very masculine
dominated civilization that profoundly
needs to reconnect with the feminine
ground of being with all that has been
separated differentiated from and in
many ways a you know oppressed
suppressed in the effort to create this
kind of powerful autonomous intelligent
advancing species which had the name in
English as in other languages with the
patriarchal word man you know it's been
man this you know the ascent of man the
dignity of man
man's conquest of space and things like
that it's that that way of summing up
the whole the whole human being as as
masculine with that image be speaks a a
profound you know separation from so
much of what it is to be human but since
I wrote that epilogue which was you know
no 30 years ago I have had thought a lot
more about the somewhat simple you know
complex but still in some way simplified
drama that I painted in those last pages
of the of the epilogue and I've come to
realize and this is partly you know here
I live in in San Francisco working with
graduate students the last 20 30 years
and very in touch with with with with
feminism with various postmodern
movements that are kind of opening up
our sense of gender and all sorts of
assumptions in patriarchy etc and and
there have been critiques within the
Jungian world for example of the what is
the feminine and what is the masculine
and also within feminism itself there
have been conflicts between different
schools and as a result of this a number
of us have been developing a perspective
that builds on Jung's great insight
because he did he made very big
breakthroughs in recognizing the dignity
of women's women and women's psychology
and also what men have cut off from
themselves that is causing them to
become soulless but at the same time he
was carrying certain patriarchal
assumptions that go way back and I mean
he
culture he came from was very
patriarchal and he still had ideas about
what was natural for a woman woman's
place was still pretty much in the home
even though he was calling on them to
develop their masculine side of
rationality and capacity for assertion
and calling on men to develop their
feminine side of intuition of feeling
relationality and so forth but as soon
as we assign rationality to one gender
over another and feeling or caring the
capacity to carry into one gender or
another we're doing something that isn't
quite fair to the complexity of those of
every human being and so what has been
emerging a group of young'uns feminists
contemporary thinkers and I have been
developing this idea of there being a
both a lunar and a solar form of the
masculine and a lunar and the solar form
of the feminine so that the the solar
masculine is the kind of patriarchal ID
ideal or a stereotype but there is a
lunar masculine that when a when a when
a father is holding his child tenderly
and and supporting his wife to go out
into the world and to be an independent
person as while still being in intimate
relationship that is his that's not just
him cultivating his feminine side it's a
part of his manhood that he's that he's
caring that he's in touch with his
emotions that he's capable of
relationality and to to assign
rationality just to him and that the
only way a woman can connect to
rationality is to develop her her inner
man in some sense impoverishes the the
full depth and breadth
of what it is to be a woman and the same
thing conversely for a man so we've been
using this more nuanced language that
recognizes that basically men certainly
need to develop their their their lunar
side the the side that is capable of
being in touch with their their feelings
their relational capacities their
emotional intelligence their intuitive
abilities to comprehend the whole beyond
kind of analytic reason and that's
that's part of their wholeness that
definitely needs to be integrated and
the same thing for for women's
development of their capacity for
autonomy for for a kind of a very
through the public life not just the
private for rational assertion in the
world and so forth that all these are I
think it it's a little too simplistic to
put it all into terms of the masculine
and the feminine even though we're
saying that the that both are in both of
us because you can never really say
anything about the feminine without
thinking about women and the master
without thinking about men and even in
really wonderful young'uns like people
who I greatly regard women young'uns
like Mary Ann Woodman who just passed
away or they they will talk about the
feminine in one sentence about the
feminine in all of us and then in the
next sentence the feminine is talking
about female psychology and they haven't
noted that they went from one meaning to
the other because it's an unconscious
conflation so we're just trying to come
up with more precise ways of showing the
rich nuance within all of us and I think
that Jordan Peterson may at times find
himself it
getting more intense blowback from
people who are hearing what seems like
slightly stereotypical assertions about
what it is to be feminine what it is to
be masculine and and if we enrich our
vocabulary objec a bit we can see that
while women certainly have of a kind of
great special relationship as it were to
this you know lunar dimension of life
the ruler of the night sky the
connection to soil depth etc and then
conversely with the with the solar but
to limit it to them and you can use that
language the feminine and unless the
masculine is still keeps perpetuating a
kind of patriarchal bifurcation you
mentioned Jordan Peterson what do you
make of the Jordan Peterson phenomena I
gave you my kind of take on it before I
think your work has been very helpful in
showing the the the value of what Jordan
Peterson is doing while also recognizing
that you know he's he it's not the
doesn't have the last word on things
that in some ways he can he can be I
think in some ways there's there's
certain simplifications that he makes
that are that are problematic and I just
gave one set of him there with masculine
feminine but it's also striking to me
how much he gets simplistically
misunderstood by both sides in the
effort to impose a kind of stereotype on
him which he I mean that famous was at a
BBC or channel 4 interview with awful
Chinaman channel 4 interview with with
Kathy Newman was
an example of that where it didn't seem
like she was really hearing the
complexity of what he was saying and
already had a pigeonhole that she was
trying to kind of hammer him into and he
was reacting against I'm I deeply admire
his capacity to engage the world with a
kind of articulate force he he's about
12 years younger than I am and I think
has just a little bit more extroverted
predisposition predispositions in him
than I do where I you know I prefer
being a little less at the focus of even
though some of my my work obviously
pushes boundaries I'm not as eager as he
seems to be or he certainly is capable
of handling just a tremendous amount of
like controvert controversy and the
onslaught of aggressive questioning and
so forth and he and he tends to do well
under aggressive questioning which not
not all of us do I think in general
aggressive questioning can make it more
difficult for the person who's being
questioned and the questioner to to on
dig deeper and unpack a more profound
understanding that might reflect
something that wouldn't have been
included had that dialogue not taken
place so but I have to say I am in real
admiration of even though I don't agree
with everything that Jordan Peterson
says it's it's I really admire his
spirit his capacity to think under
pressure
and speak to a number of audiences and
his son and the fact that he is I see in
this I think some of the force that's
coming through him is collective its he
is a he is a kind of channel for things
that haven't been said for a while and
that in some sense needed to be said
it's a you know he said he's a kind of
channel of the return of the repressed
in that sense and he has the articulate
potency of a person who was carrying
more than just his personal thinking
he's he's got a kind of collective
psyche so archetypal drive that is
informing what what and how he is saying
what he is what do you think those
things are those repressed archetypal
things well well one is to certainly his
his calling upon men to kind of
basically find their strong center again
and take responsibility for their lives
and their actions and to become
disciplined and what what DEP
psychologists would say it would be to
basically integrate the Cenex the the
that the Saturn archetype the archetype
that brings in a capacity for for for
self discipline for a backbone for
that's grounded in tradition and you you
must also give him given your work be
very pleased to see him kind of bringing
young back into the mainstream or
talking about young in such a
high-profile way yes there there are I
don't know how much that's coming in as
a return of the repressed but it but you
know it's it's interesting young himself
over the last decades seems to be going
through a quite a in elevation within
the culture and when the New York Times
gave that you know 17 pages in the New
York Times Magazine to the publication
of Young's red book
about ten years ago that was pretty much
the first positive thing that the New
York Times had allowed itself to say
about young since the very good obituary
that it wrote for him in 1961 it got
kind of overtaken by a by you know a
kind of you know narrower Freudian in
intellectual viewpoint and then an even
anti Freud at a certain point anti depth
psychology generally and I think the
more we're moving into what I would
think of as the deeper and more mature
form of the postmodern and the more
voices that are being allowed into the
cultural conversation the more young I
think is going to be recognized as not a
flawless thinker but a but a necessary
and deep one necessary for us to to
assimilate he he was carrying deep deep
truths that came from a very deep dive
that he took a kind of almost shamanic
descent that spontaneously happened to
him in the nineteen thirteen to nineteen
twenty p ria dand he came out of that
with with real treasures like basically
the end that he gave to the culture the
idea that we don't understand human
psychology unless we understand that
psyche is soul and that there is a
spiritual dimension to human existence
and to human fulfillment that if we do
not take account of it we are mutilating
ourselves and we'll never really be
psychologically healthy or his his
recognition that were all embedded in a
larger collective psyche that is
evolving and that is is going through
its own spiritual transformations and
that we're in a kind of adventure of of
consciousness individually as well as
collectively I think Jung's recce
Nishan of in the end of it on the
individual level of how important the
second half of life is and the turn
towards away from external public
achievement and more recognising that
the inner world and finding meaning and
finding a spiritual fulfillment that is
not dependent on youth and a kind of
robust quality of being in the world but
has is connecting with some deeper
sources of archetypal meaning and
purpose that give us a sense of life's
value all these are crucial gifts that
Jung gave us and and I think more and
more people are assimilating and you
mentioned SLN before and at that time
the we're talking about kind of
intellectual dark web now a
constellation of thinkers there was
quite a mighty constellation of thinkers
around Esalen I mean you can probably
tell me more of the names but I think
Joseph Campbell was there Stan Grof was
there Abraham Maslow was there yeah yeah
it was I mean it's an amazing place
first of all one of the most beautiful
places in the world but because of its
kind of mission founded in 1962 and
Abraham Maslow and his sense of it's
interesting NASA was walking was driving
through Big Sur which can sometimes be
quite foggy and it's a narrow highway on
going along a cliff and he got lost and
he saw this sign wrestlin Institute
right right after he'd been started and
he came down the hill to sort of find
out where he was and he came into the
lodge and there he saw people reading
his book towards it you know news it's
like a psychology of being and he
and and so Maslow was an that whole idea
of self-realization it was very
important so many of course there are a
lot of psychotherapists like Fritz Perls
and RD Laing and also people who were
working within the body area like IDA
Ralph and Rolfing Feldenkrais but you
also had people who were like Fritjof
Capra Joseph Campbell Gregory Bateson
gene Houston Stan Grof was there as the
scholar and residents for for 17 years
and he he brought in people like the
Rupert Sheldrake and David Bohm and
people who were kind of opening up the
Terrance came as well we had excellent
conference all the early psychedelic
pioneers were there Albert Hoffman came
from who and synthesized and discovered
LSD he came and of course stan grof and
and terrance represented like the the
next generation of and there's another
example of someone sort of hyper
articulate and and and definitely had a
kind of charismatic quality that seems
to have been infused by his psychedelic
explorations so anyway yes it was a
countercultural Malstrom and hotbed of
of new and ancient thinking practices
ideas that rippled out into the world
all well it's it's still in existence
and is a great place to visit but I
think in many ways it was during the 60s
and 70s that it really
brought its gift into the world and
disseminated it out so that many many
others have been carrying it out in
other parts of the world since then
you